<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book [
<!ENTITY % sgml.features "IGNORE">
<!ENTITY % xml.features "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % DOCBOOK_ENTS PUBLIC "-//OASIS//ENTITIES DocBook Character Entities V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/dbcentx.mod">
%DOCBOOK_ENTS;
]>
<?asciidoc-toc?>
<?asciidoc-numbered?>
<book xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0">
<info>
<title>Pipelines</title>
<date>2024-02-23</date>
<title>Pipelines</title>
<productname>OpenShift Container Platform</productname>
<productnumber>4.14</productnumber>
<subtitle>Enter a short description here.</subtitle>
<abstract>
    <para>A short overview and summary of the book's subject and purpose, traditionally no more than one paragraph long.</para>
</abstract>
<authorgroup>
    <orgname>Red Hat OpenShift Documentation Team</orgname>
</authorgroup>
<xi:include href="Common_Content/Legal_Notice.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
</info>
<chapter xml:id="about-pipelines">
<title>About {pipelines-title}</title>
<simpara>Red Hat OpenShift Pipelines is a cloud-native, continuous integration and continuous delivery (CI/CD) solution based on Kubernetes resources. It uses Tekton building blocks to automate deployments across multiple platforms by abstracting away the underlying implementation details. Tekton introduces a number of standard custom resource definitions (CRDs) for defining CI/CD pipelines that are portable across Kubernetes distributions.</simpara>
<note>
<simpara>Because Red Hat OpenShift Pipelines releases on a different cadence from OpenShift Container Platform, the Red Hat OpenShift Pipelines documentation is now available as separate documentation sets for each minor version of the product.</simpara>
<simpara>The Red Hat OpenShift Pipelines documentation is available at <link xlink:href="https://docs.openshift.com/pipelines/">https://docs.openshift.com/pipelines/</link>.</simpara>
<simpara>Documentation for specific versions is available using the version selector drop-down list, or directly by adding the version to the URL, for example, <link xlink:href="https://docs.openshift.com/pipelines/1.11">https://docs.openshift.com/pipelines/1.11</link>.</simpara>
<simpara>In addition, the Red Hat OpenShift Pipelines documentation is also available on the Red Hat Customer Portal at <link xlink:href="https://access.redhat.com/documentation/en-us/red_hat_openshift_pipelines/">https://access.redhat.com/documentation/en-us/red_hat_openshift_pipelines/</link>.</simpara>
<simpara>For additional information about the Red Hat OpenShift Pipelines life cycle and supported platforms, refer to the <link xlink:href="https://access.redhat.com/support/policy/updates/openshift#pipelines">Platform Life Cycle Policy</link>.</simpara>
</note>
</chapter>
</book>
